In this video we will launch the stress test to find a test
في هذا الفيديو سنفتتح اختبار الإجهاد لإيجاد مدخلات
on which our main solution and alternative solutions differ,
يختلف فيها حلنا عن حلول أخرى
use this test to debug our main solution and fix it.
سنستخدم هذا الاختبار لتنقيح وإصلاح حلنا
So we save the file.
لنقم بحفظ هذا الملف
Now we will compile this file because we will want to run it.
الآن سنترجم هذا الملف لأننا نريد تشغيله
And to compile this file, we go to the section Solving Programming Assignments.
ولترجمة هذا الملف، نذهب إلى قسم حل المسائل البرمجية
We look at the C++ Flags, copy them, and then use them to compile our file.
نلقي نظرة على علامات مترجم السي++، ننسخهم ونستخدمهم لترجمة ملفنا
Also, of course, specify which file want to compile and
وبالطبع عليك كتابة اسم الملف المراد ترجمته
also the name for the output file will be stress_test, without .cpp.
واسم الملف الخارج سيكون سترس_تيست، بدون الامتداد cpp.
So we compile our stress test and then we launch it and see what happens.
وهكذا قمنا بترجمة اختبار الإجهاد بعدها نشغله ونرى ما الذي سيحدث
So we see, our screen was filled with a lot of lines.
وهكذا نرى، شاشتنا مملوءه بالسطور
Actually, those lines were words, OK, and some numbers,
حسناً، هذه السطور مكونة من الكلمة تمام (OK)، وبعض الأرقام،
like number n from 2 to 11, and input numbers, which are big.
كالعدد ن من 2 إلى 11، والأعداد المدخلة، وهي ذات قيمة كبيرة
And there are a lot of tests for which our solutions didn't differ, and
وهناك الكثير من الحالات حيث لا يوجد اختلاف بين الحلين
that all went pretty fast.
تم التنفيذ بسرعة لا بأس بها
And then in the end, we have number 11, which is n, and
وفي الأخير هناك العدد 11 وهو ن
then 11 big numbers, which is the input test, and then the words,
و 11 عدداً كبيراً، وهي المدخلات للاختبار، وبعدها العبارة
Wrong answer and two very big numbers which are different, which are the answers
حل غير صحيح وعددان كبيران غير متساويان هذان هما الحلان
correspondingly of the first and the second solution we implemented.
بالترتيب الحل الأول والثاني والذي قمنا بتنفيذهما
So now,
فالآن،
we already have a test on which at least one of our solution runs incorrectly.
لدينا اختبار فشل فيه على الأقل أحد الحلين
But it is very hard to work with this test because we have 11 numbers and
ولكنه من الصعب العمل على هذا الاختبار حيث أن هناك 11 عدداً
they are very big and the answer to this problem is even bigger.
وكلهم أعداد كبيرة والناتج أيضاً عددٌ أكبر
So let us try to find a smaller test on which our solution still fails.
لذلك فلنحاول إيجاد اختبار أصغر يفشل فيه حلنا
Usually we can create a very small test with this technique.
عادةً، يمكننا إنشاء اختبار صغير جداً باستخدام هذه التقنية
So let's go back to our code, stress_test.cpp.
فلنعد إلى ملف الشفرة، المسمى سترس_تيست
And let's decrease the restrictions on n and on the numbers.
ولننقص الحدود على العدد ن وعلى الاعداد المدخلة
So, for example, we want our number n to be no more than 5,
ولذا على سبيل المثال نريد أن لا يزيد العدد ن على 5
then we first generate a random number modulo 4 so it will be from 0 to 3.
ولتحقيق ذلك، نولد عدد عشوائي ذو مقياس 4 حتى نحصل على عدد بين 0 و3
And then, after adding 2, it will be from 2 to 5.
وبعد إضافة 2 إليه، سيكون عدداً عشوائياً بين 2 إلى 5
And also, we want our numbers to be less than 10.
وكذلك، نريد للأعداد المدخلة أن تكون اقل من 10
So we just generate numbers modulo ten.
ولهذا نولد عدد ذو مقياس 10
And that's everything we change.
وهذه كل التغييرات التي سنحدثها.
Now we save the file.
الآن نحفظ الملف.
We recompile with the same options.
نعيد ترجمته بنفس علامات المترجم السابقة
And we again launch our stress test.
ومجدداً نشغل اختبار الإجهاد
Now, we found a test on which solutions differ even faster.
ونحصل الآن على اختبار يختلف فيه الحلان بشكل اسرع
Only maybe five or seven tests were OK.
ربما خمسة أو سبعة اختبارات فقط اتفقت نتائجها
And now we have a test with five numbers, which are 2, 9, 3, 1, and 9,
ولدينا الآن اختبار من 5 أعداد: 2؛ 9؛ 3؛ 1؛ 9
on which our solutions differ.
يحث تختلف فيه نتيجة الحلين
And the answer of the first solution is 81.
وناتج الحل الأول هو 81
the second solution is 27.
وناتج الحل الثاني هو 27
Which one of those is correct?
أيهما الحل الصحيح؟
Of course, the first one is correct, because we have numbers 9 and
بالطبع، الحل الأول هو الصحيح، لانه لدينا العدد 9
second 9, which are the biggest in the input, and their product is 81.
ومرة أخرى العدد 9، وهما العددين الأكبر في المدخلات، وحاصل ضربهما هو 81
So our first naive solution gives a correct answer, but
وبناءً على ذلك، حلنا الأول المباشر يعطي نتيجة صحيحة
our second fast solution gives an incorrect answer.
بينما حلنا الثاني الأسرع يعطي نتيجة خاطئة.
And let's think why that can be.
ولنفكر في السبب وراء هذا.
Well, that can be if it multiplies wrong numbers from the array.
حسناً، سيحدث هذا إذا قام بضرب العددين الخطأ من المصفوفة
So, let's go back in the code and check which are those numbers.
لنعد إلى الشفرة ولنتحقق أي عددين هما.
We can go into the code and
يمكننا العودة للشفرة
we look into the code for function MaxPairwiseProductFast.
ونلقي نظرة على الشفرة الخاصة بالوظيفة (أو الدالة) ماكس_بييروايز_برودكت_فاست
It's very convenient that we have a separate function for
انه لمن المناسب جدا أننا نملك على وظيفة (أو دالة) منفصلة
this solution because the error should be localized somewhere here.
لهذا الحل لأن الخطأ يجب أن يكون في مكان ما هنا.
So to simplify our goal of debugging,
لتبسيط هدفنا في تنقيح الحل،
let's output the indices of the maximum number and of the second
فلنقم بعرض فهرس العدد الأكبر وفهرس العدد الأكبر الثاني
maximum number that at least this function thinks are two maximums in the array.
أو على الأقل ما تعتقد الوظيفة انهما العددان الأكبر في المصفوفة
So we output them to cout.
وسنقوم بإخراجهما ألى الخرْج القياسي عن طريق سي_أوت
First the first index, then a space to separate them,
أولاً الفهرس الأول، ثم مسافة للفصل بينهما،
then the second index, and then newline character.
بعدها الفهرس الثاني، ويلي ذلك رمز السطر الجديد
So we save our program.
وهكذا نحفظ البرنامج.
We again recompile it, and we again launch the stress test.
نقوم بترجمته مجدداً، ونشغل اختبار الإجهاد مرة أخرى.
So note that although we generate random tests, it is safe to
ولاحظ أنه رغم أننا نولد أعداد عشوائية، إلا أنه لا مشكلة في
launch our stress test again because those are pseudo random.
تشغيل اختبار الإجهاد مجددا لأنها أعداد شبه عشوائية.
The sequence of generated random values is the same.
حيث أن قيم المتتالية المتولدة هي نفسها في كل مرة.
So this is a reproducible test.
ولذلك بالإمكان إعادة نفس الاختبار أكثر من مرة.
So now, again, we have the same test in which two solutions differ
وهكذا مجدداً، لدينا نفس الاختبار حيث تختلف فيه نتيجتي
with five numbers, the same five numbers.
الاختبار ذو الخمسة أعداد نفسها.
And now, under the line with five numbers, we have another line which says 1 2.
ولكن الآن، تحت السطر حيث تظهر الأعداد الخمسة لدينا سطر آخر يظهر فيه 1 2
This is actually our debug output, which means that the index of the first number,
هذا في خرْج التنقيح الذي قمنا بإضافته ويعني أن فهرس العدد الأول
which is maximum, is 1 and it corresponds to number
وهو العدد الأكبر، يساوي 1 وهذا يقابل العدد
9 because we enumerate our numbers from 0 in our C++ array.
9 لأننا في لغة السي بلس بلس نبدأ الفهرس من الصفر  في المصفوفة
And the second number has index 2, and this is number 3, again,
والعدد الثاني يحمل الفهرس 2، وهذا يقابل العدد 3، مجدداً
because we enumerate from 0.
لان الفهرس يبدأ من الصفر.
So, our fast solution thinks that the second maximum number
وهكذا، يظن حلنا السريع أن العدد الثاني من حيث القيمة
in the array is the number 3 instead of number 9, which is in position four.
في المصفوفة يساوي 3 عوضا عن العدد 9، الذي يحمل الفهرس 4
So let's go back to the code and see why it happened.
لنعد مجددا إلى الشفرة، لنرى لماذا حدث هذا.
Again, we open the file with the code.
مجددا، نفتح ملف الشفرة.
We go to the function MaxPairwiseProductFast.
نذهب إلى الوظيفة ماكس_بييروايز_برودك_فاست.
We ignore the code for
نتجاهل الشفرة الخاصة بالجزء
the max_index1 and we're very interested in the code for max_index2.
ماكس_إنديكس1 ولكننا مهتمون جدا بالجزء الخاص ب ماكس_إنديكس2
So now let's look at this complex if expression,
لنلقي نظرة على هذا العبارة الشرطية المعقدة،
where we try to determine whether a number at position j
حيث نحاول تحديد ما إذا كان أي عدد في الموقع ج
may be a new maximum, which is different from the maximum we've already found.
ربما يكون هو العدد الأكبر التالي بشرط أن لا يكون نفس العدد الأكبر الأول
And let's look more closely at this particular first condition.
ولندقق في هذا الشرط الأول بالتحديد
So here, what we do is we check that number at position number j is
وهنا ما نقوم به هو فحص ما إذا كان العدد في الموقع ج
different from the maximum we've already found.
يختلف عن العدد الأكبر الأول
But that's exactly the problem.
ولكن هذه هي المشكلة بالتحديد.
What we need is instead, that j
ما نحتاجه بدلاً عن هذا، هو أن
is different from max_index1 because we don't want to find the same number, but
تختلف ج عن المتغير ماكس_إنديكس1 لأننا لا نريد أن نحصل على نفس العدد، ولكن
we can find number which is equal to the first found maximum.
أن يكون بالإمكان الحصول على عدد يساوي العدد الأكبر ولكن في موقع آخر
So, instead of this comparison, what we actually need is to compare j,
ولذلك، بدلاً عن هذه المقارنة، ما نجتاحه حقا هو مقارنة ج
To max_index1.
بالمتغير ماكس_إنديكس1.
If we fix our code this way, then we will be at least able
إذا قمنا بإصلاح شفرتنا بهذا الشكل، عندها سنتمكن على الأقل من
to find the second number 9 in our input array 2 9 3 1 9, which we saw.
إيجاد العدد الأكبر الثاني 9 في مصفوفتنا 2 9 3 1 9،  والتي رأينها سابقاُ.
So let's see how it goes after we fix this.
فلنرى ما سيحدث بعدما نقوم بإصلاح هذه المشكلة
So we save the file, we again recompile it with the same options and
سنحفظ الملف ثم مجدداً نعيد ترجمته بنفس علامات المترجم السابقة
we launch our stress test.
نشغل اختبار الإجهاد
So now what we see is a screen which is very quickly filling with
ما نراه الآن هو شاشة تمتلئ بسرعة
some numbers, some words OK, and then some numbers again and words OK.
ببعض الأعداد وبعض الكلمات التي تقول تمام (OK) ويتكرر هذا الأمر مراراً.
And we should wait for some time, for maybe 10 seconds or
ويجب أن ننتظر لبعض الوقت، ربما ل 10 ثواني أو
even 30 seconds to be sure that we cannot find a test in which our solutions differ.
حتى 30 ثانية حتى نتأكد أنه لا يوجد اختبار تختلف فيه النتيجتان
But, by now, it seems that that is the case.
ويبدو حتى الآن، أن الحل صحيح
And in the next video, we will do more testing and
وفي الفيديو القادم، سنقوم بالمزيد من الاختبارات
then submit our main solution to the system and see how it goes.
ثم نقوم بتسليم حلنا إلى نظام التقييم الآلي وسنرى ما الذي سيحدث